哈喽大家好
Hello everyone
最近这个天气有点凉
It's been quite chilly these days
所以我准备了20斤牛油
so, I've got 20kg of beef fat
做一顿麻辣牛油火锅来吃
to prepare a spicy hotpot
跟我伯爷还有我们一家人吃
for my uncle and the whole family
四伯爷你吃得辣不辣哦
Uncle, should I make it spicy?
不要整很辣嘛
(Not too spicy)
今天晚上我们一起烫个火锅吃
We are having hotpot for dinner
好好好
(Great)
来 漆二娃端过去
Qi Erwa, hold this for me
我这里准备了一些姜还有葱
I've got some ginger and spring onion
做火锅的话这些东西是少不了的
These are essential for a good hotpot
这里总共是20斤牛油
So, for the 20kg of beef fat
然后配了3斤姜跟这个3斤大葱
we need 3kg each for ginger and spring onion
用这个来炸这个油
we will deep fry them in the fat
炸得更香
for a nice flavor
我把这个切好了再去配香料
Let me first chop these before preparing the spices.
漆二娃
Qi Erwa!
嗯
(Yes?)
不是你来切我去弄香料
Why don't you do the chopping?
正好你拿去练哈刀工
You could use some practice
现在我们来配点香料
Now, the spices
我们家庭里面就少放一些
We don't need that much for everyday cooking at home
因为普通老百姓掌握不了这些香料的量
it's hard to get the amount right if you are not experienced
如果香料放多了之后
If you put too much
做的不好的话可能有一些苦涩味
it might become bitter and astringent
放点这个去籽的草果
Tsaoko fruits in, without the seeds
然后放点八角
then Star Anise
这个三奈
some Aromatic Ginger
还有这个桂皮 桂皮把它弄小一点
and some Cinnamon, in small pieces
放点这个陈皮
some dried Tangerine peel
再放几片香叶
a few Bay leaves
香叶少一点放多了味道很冲
Don't put too many as they are very pungent
放几颗丁香
now a few cloves
放点白蔻
a few Baikou (fruit of Amomum cardamomum)
再放一颗罗汉果
one Monk Fruit (fruit of Fructus momordicae)
因为这个火锅的话有点上火
Spicy hotpot induces yeet-hay
放一下这个进去润一下肺
so we need the Monk Fruit to compensate that and ease our lungs
最后再倒点白酒进去
Lastly we pour some Chinese spirits in
其实放白酒把它湿润一下
mainly to soak the spices a little bit
好让这个香料能够更好的吧这个香味释放出来
in order to bring the aroma out when frying
好
Okay
再放一点花椒
Now, the Szechuan pepper
花椒单独用这个白酒泡
mix them separately with the Chinese spirits
用白酒浸过的香料也不容易糊
it prevents the Szechuan peppers from burning
然后更容易入味
and makes it easier to introduce the flavour
出味道
and to get the flavour out
这个水是倒来做糍粑辣椒的
We will use the water to prepare the chili paste
要放这么多辣椒吗
(This many?)
做糍粑辣椒都嘛
Sure, because we need to chop them later
其实我们做火锅底料的话
For the hotpot base
这个干辣椒非常的重要
we need choose the right types of dried chili pepper
这个是子弹头不是特别辣
This one is called "bullet head", it's not too spicy
待会儿再配点灯笼椒进去
Later we will put some dried bell peppers
因为我伯爷说不要吃太辣
Uncle doesn't like it to be too spicy
所以就选择了这个辣椒
that's why we picked these types.
这个糍粑辣椒就是火锅底料里面非常重要的一个
chili paste is a key ingredient in hotpot
就是一定要把它煮软然后把它剁碎
We need to biol the chili peppers and chop them
剁碎了炒在牛油里面的话它非常非常的红
then fry them in beef fat to get the bright red colour out
很香很红也不是特别辣
also to release the aroma without being too spicy
刚哥应该差不多可以了吧
(I think it's amlmost ready)
你过来看看
(Can you have a look?)
嗯 可以啦
Yes that's ready
这个辣椒就是
You know it's ready
煮到它这个你看
when you get the red color
有红色的能够捏出红色的东西就可以了
once you sqeeze it with your fingers
就说明已经OK了
Then it's OK.
我给你说这个
To prepare this
这个先这样
First you slice them like this
把它切细点然后再拿这个来砍
then chop them into small pieces
把它切细了之后就这样子
like this
就可以这样子宰了
now you finely chop them
这个糍粑辣椒以前在我们老家都是用怼窝（石臼）来钟
We used to use make the paste with a mortar and a pestle.
但是现在没有怼窝（石臼）的话就用刀慢慢剁
We don't have them now, so we must chop with a knife.
剁细了也是一样的
It's the same if you chop them finely
懂了吗
Get it?
懂了
(Yes)
但是
(well, in theory)
但是手不一定懂啊
(maybe not in practice)
剁到这个样子就差不多了
It's ready like this
嗯
(OK)
这个不用剁得太细
It doesn't have to be too fine，
但是能够起蓉就可以了
as long as it turns into a paste
它能够贴到刀上起容就可以了
like this, when it gets sticky on the knife.
好 现在我们要开始做这个火锅底料了
Alright, let's start cooking
现在把牛油全部放到锅里面去
First, put the beef fat in the pot
把它烧化
Melt it down
这熬来可以装起来吗
(Can we keep it for the future?)
可以啊
Sure
这个可以放得到一段时间
You can even keep it for a while.
火烧大点
More heat.
天都黑了完了一会儿吃到这个火锅害怕摸到吃哦
It's getting dark soon. Are we going to eat it in the dark?
有灯都嘛
(We have lamps right?)
我们吃上这锅火锅的话应该要等到1个多小时以后了
We might still need one hour to prepare this hotpot.
这个油温已经差不多了现在我要下姜葱下去
OK the temperature is good enough for the ginger and spring onion
这个姜一盆一盆的放有点奢侈
That's a bit luxurious isn't it, to use this much?
我们这个料下去的时候不能一盆一起全部一下子倒下去
Be careful, you should not pour it in all together
就怕这个油扑起来
the hot oil may splash.
所以要慢慢的抓
You should do it sloly by hand.
姜下去没一会儿然后我们要把这个葱一起放下去
Gingers in, now let's put the spring onion in.
火锅香不香全靠这一步
This is the most crucial step to determine the aroma.
好 现在我们就慢慢的把这个姜葱炸干炸香
Alright, we just need to slowly fry them until they are dry and fragrant
炸干炸香之后再捞出来
then we can take them out
好啦我们这个姜葱已经金黄酥脆了
OK, the ginger and spring onion are golden and crispy
毕竟我们只要的是姜葱的香味
We only need their flavour and aroma
不要这个黑色的东西
not the leftovers
好 现在我们这个油已经烧得差不多了
OK the oil is ready
大概5成油温的样子
at about medium temperature
现在我们把刚刚剁好的糍粑辣椒放下去
chili paste in
再不炒的话等一下天都要黑完了
We really need to fry it before it gets too dark
这个也同样一样少少的放
Same as before, put it in slowly and carefully
要不然这个油会扑出来
to prevent the oil from splashing
我们这个糍粑辣椒下去的话就是为了
We fry the chili paste to extract the
要这个颜色还有这个辣味
red colour and the spiciness.
慢慢的炒
Stir gently
我们见到这个油变成红色的时候
Once the oil turs red
转小火慢慢来
lower the heat
好 这个油已经变红了
OK, it's turning red
现在把香料放进去
Now, let's put the spices in.
为什么我们这个香料要先放呢
Why do we put them in now?
因为这个没有打碎的
Because they are not ground
所以提前放下去多熬一会儿
so, it takes longer for them
要不然香味出不来
to release the aroma
好 现在香料下去差不多
OK the spices are ready
然后下这个灯笼椒多下一点
Let's put more of the dried bell peppers
大家都不能吃辣
We are not eating too spicy today
但是这个灯笼椒很香
But the bell peppers are very fragrant.
现在这个油已经很红了
The oil is turning red.
在我们闻到香味的时候再把豆瓣酱放下去
The aroma is also there, so it's time for the Doubanjiang (chili bean paste)
20斤（牛油）的话可能要放3-4斤豆瓣酱
You need 3-4 kg for the 20kg of beef fat
这个豆瓣酱主要是调咸味
The paste mainly provides saltiness
还有香味
and aroma
所以到这一步的时候我们基本上就不去看时间
There is no fixed cooking time for this step
我们这一步就看豆瓣酱
We need to keep checking the paste
豆瓣酱的水份略干
When it gets a bit drier
闻到香的时候散籽的时候
also, when you can smell the aroma and (散籽不太确定啥意思)
再下其它辅料
it's time for the other ingredients
现在非常的红亮这个
What a bright red colour.
好 这个豆瓣酱已经开始酥香酥香的了
The paste is also crispy and aromatic.
开始放其它的料
Time for the rest of the ingredients.
现在把这个豆豉放下去
Black bean paste in
豆豉是增香的 特别的香
It's also for the aroma
好现在豆瓣酱已经很香很香了
OK it smells great.
这个时候再把花椒放下去
Now the Szechuan peppers
这个花椒
Remember
是用白酒浸泡过的
these have bee soaked in Chinese spirits
吃得麻的话可以多放一点
you can put more init if you like the numbness.
好啦 花椒的水份已经差不过了
Alright, it's getting dried.
放点醪糟 放这么一点就够了
Let's put a bit of Laozao (Fermented glutinous rice)
这个不能多放
not too much
这个放下去的话炒一会儿
Let it fry for a while
闻到醪糟的香味就可以放冰糖了
When we smell the aroma of Laozao, we can put the crystal sugar in.
冰糖也不用太多 这么一点就可以了
Also, not too much, this will do.
因为在做火锅的时候
That's because, later,
都还要再继续加糖来调味的
we will add sugar when we eat.
好 差不多了
OK almost done.
最后再放一点白酒
Last step, the Chinese spirits.
放多少呢
How much do we need?
3瓶盖
Three "caps"
1盖
One
2盖
Two
3盖
Three
让它再挥发一下
Let the alcohol evaporate a little bit.
这高度白酒放下去会非常的香
It smells very good with the Chinese spirits.
好啦 这个火锅底料就差不多完成了
Alright, we are almost done.
待会儿再把它装起来
We will pour it out
装到托盘里面
into a tray
这个就相当于我们的模具
The tray works as a mold.
它凉了之后就是这样子的
It will stay in shape once it cools down.
等一下小煮一锅来试一下
Let's try it in a pot
现在天气已经晚了
It's getting late
然后不好拍了
It's not easy to film anymore.
我们今天晚上就将就一下先吃吃了再说
We will give it a try first tonight.
等下一次这个火锅底料硬了之后
Later, when the sause gets solidified
切下来 再跟大家分享
we cut it and show you
调这个底料
how to season the hotpot
好啦 本期视频就到这里结束
Alright, that's it for today
拜拜
Bye-bye!